my bed my bridal all for misery
and i cannot
i cannot save my child from death
this is one of the most shocking stories ever written
a mother a princess has lost her city and her husband in war
now she has to face the news that she is to be sold into slavery
and her only son killed
this film version of an ancient greek play called trojan women
has become a classic
the first time i saw it i was moved to tears and it still moves me now
it is a play about the most charged aspects of human life
love war sacrifice fear and death
and although it is set amongst the gods myths
and peoples of ancient greece it is still utterly gripping today
it is one of the main reasons i study classics
an athenian called euripides wrote this play
a little under two and a half thousand years ago
back then he was often ridiculed as an angry young man
but over time his plays have come to symbolise
the incredible sophistication of ancient greek civilisation
that civilisation has influenced almost every aspect of our lives
not just drama but politics language philosophy
art and architecture
to understand ourselves it turns out
we need to understand the ancient greeks
and the best seat from which to do that for my money
is in the theatre
this series is about how ancient drama changed our world
it's the story of dramatists
like aeschylus sophocles and euripides
who revolutionised storytelling through plays
like trojan women antigone oedipus and the oresteia
it's the story of how the ancient greeks
gave birth to tragedy and comedy
and it's the story of how theatre spread throughout greece and beyond
becoming a benchmark of civilisation
not just for greeks but for the world
then and now
in this episode i want to journey to athens
to explore how drama first began
from the very start it was about more than just entertainment
it was a reaction to real events it was a driving force in history
and it was deeply connected to athenian democracy
in fact the story of theatre is the story of athens
the cultural hub of ancient greece
and the stage for one of the greatest shows on earth
the story of drama as we know it begins in a particular place
and a particular time
athens in the 6th century before christ
at that time greece was not a single country
but a mass of competing citystates or poleis
the greek term describing a body of citizens
but in the late 6th century the polis of athens
pulled ahead of the others
politically economically and culturally
in the last part of the 6th century bc
athens was the breeding ground for two extraordinary inventions
the first was democracy
athens was ruled not by kings or by cliques of aristocrats
but by the votes of its own citizens
but the second was theatre
athens invented an entirely new art form drama
and these two inventions were tightly intertwined
at the beating heart of athenian society
and both of them were the result
of an extraordinary cultural revolution
at this time the whole of ancient greek culture
underwent a historic transformation
the revolution extended from architecture to literature
from vase painting to philosophy
you can see the impact of that revolution clearly
in how greek sculpture developed
in the middle 6th century it was rigid stylised
lacking movement and life
but then things began to change
by the 5th century greek artists began
to produce some of the greatest lifelike sculptures ever made
it all amounted not just to a newlooking world
but to a whole new view of the world
we call it the classical world
and in this groundbreaking epoch
drama was perhaps the biggest innovation of them all
tales of love death and war had always been passed on
by storytellers and epic poems like homer's iliad
and savage myths had been celebrated in choral dance and song
but the athenians added actors and invented the idea of performance
these epic stories would now play out not only in the mind
but live on stage
this was more than innovation this was a revolution
never before in the greek tradition that we know of
in the greek storytelling tradition
were things enacted rather than narrated
so instead of having and then the king drew his sword and said
instead a person actually draws a sword and speaks
i know we sort of say well children do that
but to do it with serious storytelling
with storytelling that actually delves into
important roots in human behaviour
that is a very new step and to have it done in front of you
i think that must have been a very very startling innovation
actor the son of thyestes
ancient greek drama looked
and sounded very different from drama as we know it today
there were no more than three or four actors
there was a chorus who interrupted the action with song and dance
and all the performers wore masks
when an actor began to enact rather than narrate
there's a kind of dangerousness about that
that the actor has to become a woman
the actor has to become a slave
the actor perhaps even more dangerously
has to become a god and it's almost as if the mask
is a kind of signal of the profession
that protects the actor against the danger of doing these things
actor blood shoot of aetrius
'the chorus are costumed and masked in an identical'
or near identical way and they move and speak as a group
the chorus is not a bunch of individuals
for the greeks the chorus was a group
in which in a sense they submerged their identity
and what the chorus does is in its groupness
it tries to make sense of what it's witnessing
they're deeply emotionally involved and the suffering becomes a song
and the chorus as a group with its group response
sings its choral lyrics
actor he plotted it singlehanded the people will stone him
chorus you don't stand a chance
it seems to me that the crucial thing is that it is simultaneously
a very strong emotional experience
and a very strong thought experience
when the greeks came to analyse their new art form
they discerned three different types of play
two of which we still have with us today tragedy and comedy
but in many ways modern tragedy has actually changed
from how ancient tragedy worked
for us tragedy is a play with a sad ending
but for the ancient greeks tragedy was a play
in which the events offered the audience a tough decision
and because no real ancient tragedy ends conclusively
siding with one course of action or another
what it does is face the audience with a problem
what would they do if they were in the same situation
take one of the most famous plays ever written
oedipus the king by sophocles
it tells the story of oedipus
a man who was destined to kill his father and marry his mother
although this outcome is predicted by an oracle
oedipus himself makes a series of free choices
that lead to its fulfilment
choices that would have posed serious questions for the audience
the play ends with oedipus blinding himself in despair
the issues dealt with in tragedy were often so disturbing
that the plays were nearly always set away from athens
in the land of myth and legend or at very least a far away city
and after a series of tragedies
the athenians were offered a satyr play
now we don't have this any more today
but effectively the satyrs
were the halfmale halfgoat companions of the god of revelry
who would be allowed to run around the stage
doing lots of lewd and bawdy things as a bit of light relief
but what we do have today is comedy
and ancient comedy just like tragedy
spoke directly to contemporary athenians
usually set in a topsyturvy version of real life
or in a realm of fantasy they poked fun at contemporary athens
the birds is a play that mocks the athenian obsession
with litigation and politics
it tells the story of two men
who are tired of a life of law courts and civic duties
to escape they turn themselves into birds
and create a bird cityinthesky called cloud cuckoo land
where they reject all attempts to impose athenianstyle law and order
both comedy and tragedy sought to have a direct bearing
on life in athens
and most fascinating of all is how they seamlessly blended together
religion and myth with contemporary politics
this means that a play like the oresteia by aeschylus
can start with a mythic tale from the trojan wars
where agamemnon is murdered by his wife and avenged by his son orestes
but can end in a courtroom in democratic athens
with orestes on trial for the murder of his mother
the oresteia is one of the biggest hits in antiquity
it's also one of the very few trilogies that we've got
so what you have is three tragedies
and in this case it's got a connected story
how does tragedy take this smorgasbord if you like
and make it into a story
well it's not the same problem for the ancient greeks
as it might be for us
you know there's not this idea of anachronism
your mythical world with the gods with the trojan war
all of this that we've had in the first parts with the trilogy
can then end in that third part with a law court in athens
which would have been familiar of course
from 1st century contemporary athens
so you have this brilliant genre
where you can zoom from your present day into the past
and bring your past into your present day
and it's that relationship
that tragedy uses to say things about its contemporary society
to find out more about how drama and democratic athens
became so intimately connected
i want to look at how theatre first emerged
everything in ancient greece
came under the auspices of a particular god
and the god controlling theatre was called dionysus
he was also the god of wine and revelry
and many scholars think that theatre evolved directly
out of the choral songs performed in honour of dionysus
but there's also something else going on here
something that is suggested by the ruins
at a place called thorikos near athens
this region was once home to the ancient athenian silver mines
but is also the site
of the oldest stonebuilt theatre in the greek world
we're in an industrial heartland of the ancient athenian state
with the ore washeries and the mineshafts
just beyond the theatre here
the first phase of this theatre is late 6th century
and that puts it in the same time
as the invention of athenian democracy itself
which throws up another question
just what is the relationship between theatre and democracy
and how did the two help each other into being
it's a question that has been debated by scholars for centuries
were theatre and democracy connected from the very start
now i actually buy into the story that tragic drama
is a democratic invention
i have a particular take
because i am one of those who think that athenian tragic drama
was deeply strongly politicised
not just it happened in a polis but it happened in a polis
of a particular sort and could not have happened before athens
became a polis of that particular sort a democratic one
the theatrical side seems to coincide
fairly closely with the political identity
theatrical activities of some sort or another
were one of the ways in which they expressed the fact
that now they all belonged together
this was the place to which they came and in which they acted
it's about you know
the local community feeling itself to be a local community
i'm on my way to visit one of the smaller athenian communities
to try and find some more proof
about the connection between drama and politics
i want to see what the archaeology itself has to say
now neither for theatre nor for democracy
was there any kind of immaculate conception
nor were either born into the fullydeveloped form
that we recognize them today
both developed arminarm over time
and all around us as we drive in attica
we can see the building blocks
the basis of the athenian democratic system
people tend to think of athenians as city dwellers
but much of the population
actually lived in village communities called demes
there were 139 demes making up the athenian democracy
and each deme governed itself
the deme i'm looking for is one of the remotest
it's called rhamnous
the people who lived here were mostly farmers
but all the male citizens voted for the council
and on local regulations and on bylaws
and right at the heart of the community
are the remains of what was once a theatre
this is what i've come looking for on this very hot afternoon
an inscription that shows us democracy
at its most local level in operation
dionisoi to dionysus
hypo tes boules from the boule
the local council controlling this deme here in attica
and it's to dionysus because yes you've guessed it
we're in a theatre a theatre the space of dionysus
the privileged seats for the distinguished local clientele
and the stage set out before us
religion politics theatre
at democracy's most local level
these theatres really were far more than just places of entertainment
they were places where the whole deme would gather together
noone's going to bother to build a theatre
just for a couple of days of drama a year
but the theatres here
at the lowest most basic level of the athenian democracy
seem to have also been used as multipurpose civic spaces
giving them allyearround potential not just for drama
but also for democracy and democratic action itself
and that is what the archaeology is really beginning to uncover
not only the demes but the deme theatres
spreading across all of attica
the use of theatres for democratic activity
seems to have been the case not just in the demes
but in the city of athens itself
every year the democratic authorities spent a fortune
on the great dionysia festival a drama competition
that took place in the theatre of dionysus
in honour of the god of theatre
it's through understanding the different stages of this festival
that we can get closer to understanding what ancient athenians
experienced when they watched and created drama
the festival began with a procession
a rowdy affair with feasting drinking
and a great crowd of people parading through the streets
with a statue of the god and a small herd of sacrificial animals
when it reached the altar of the 12 olympian gods in the marketplace
the first thing that happened was a holy dance
the cult of dionysus is very much
a psychological thing
wine was of course very important
everyone knows that
but the thing was that by drinking wine
you were getting closer to the god
and the more wine you drink the more you step out of yourself
and get closer to the god
and that is also what happens when you're dancing
you're getting outside yourself so to say but also by for example
wearing a mask
the ancient people thought that when you were wearing a mask
you really become someone else
and the greek word is it's ecstasies
so ec out stasis of one's self of one's stance yes
and that's our ecstasy it is the ecstasy as we know it
the ecstasy of the god yeah
the procession then surged through the streets
along a route lined with tripods
monuments put up by the proud sponsors of the winning plays
often politicians
they spent fortunes funding dramatic productions
and marked their victories with monuments like this one
put up by a winner from the 4th century bc
so the drama festival was more than an opportunity for staging plays
it was a chance for the leading figures of athens
to stage their generosity and their success to the whole city
finally having wound its way right around the acropolis
the procession emerged noisily into the precinct of dionysus
by now the participants were becoming a single entity
it was a religious but also a political incident actually
you know the whole city so to say
steps toward the god
in order to worship the god
and they show not only their piety
but also that they belong together
so it's an extraordinary idea isn't it
that when they take their seats in theatre it's no longer
we would say in english it's no longer joe bloggs and somebody
it's no longer the farmer and the individuals
it is a collective of people with a new identity
which is that of worshippers of the god dionysus yes correct
it's a bit different to going to the theatre today right it is indeed
all of this put the audience into a receptive state
for the drama competition that was to follow
but first as they took their seats in the theatre
there was one more important set of rituals to come
the audience were seated here
perhaps in the same groupings as when they went to war
the citizens of athens who were acting on the stage
were acting in the same groups as when they went to war
and in the front seats of the theatre were the reserved seats
for various priests of the city and for the important civic officials
and then before the plays began there were a series of events
first a libation an offering to the gods were poured
in the centre of the stage by the generals
the military generals of the city
then a parade of tribute
of all the money paid by the cities and states of the athenian empire
to athens was literally taken across the stage
paraded in front of an audience that contained members
from those same citystates which had to pay all that money
then a list of all those who had benefited the city in some way
was read out
and finally onto the stage were brought the orphans
those whose parents had died fighting for the city in battle
and whom the city would now
take on the expenses of bringing up and educating
they came on dressed themselves in the armour of war
and took their seats their special seats here in the theatre
only then could the plays begin
from dawn until dusk for five days
the citizen audience watched three playwrights
each put on three tragedies as well as a farcical satyr play
and some comedies
at their heart were issues of justice and loyalty
war and peace vengeance and compassion
which sent powerful messages to the citizen audience
in the centuries of athens' greatness
over 1000 plays were written for the dionysia
but today just 32 of them survive in full
and those 32 have survived in part
because they were considered to be the greatest
and they were all written by just three people
aeschylus sophocles euripides
the great tragedians of the 5th century bc
aeschylus was the first
he was the author of the oresteia
the only whole trilogy to have survived
sophocles wrote two of the most enduring plays
oedipus the king and antigone
which tells the tragic story of oedipus' daughter
who is sentenced to death
for breaking the law and burying her rebel brother
but of all the playwrights euripides is now considered
in many ways to have been the best
he wrote the play medea with its shocking tale
of a woman betrayed by her husband
who takes revenge by killing her own children
the playwrights of ancient athens were all gurus of the city
in one form or another aeschylus the war hero
sophocles the civic official
and euripides the sort of enfant terrible of athenian society
the greek word for playwright is didaskalos
which means trainer or teacher
now in part that refers to the playwright's role
in training the chorus for their play
but many believe it also refers to the role of the playwright
in training the audience for participation in democracy itself
if we take sophocles' ajax as an example
it's a retelling of a classic myth
set in the time of the legendary war between the greeks and the trojans
and on the one hand it's just that
but on the other it's also a lesson
a lesson in the sacrifices that have to be made for democracy to work
ajax was one of the warriors who fought with the greeks at troy
after the death of achilles the greatest hero of them all
the greeks take a vote on who should get his weapons
they choose odysseus not ajax and ajax is furious
unable to accept the result of the vote he goes on a killing spree
and ultimately consumed by the shame of his actions
he is driven to suicide
the motor of this play is a vote
a process that would have been very familiar
to the democratic citizens of ancient athens
but it's a vote that ajax refuses to accept
ajax is the antithesis of the good democratic citizen
but the play also goes further
because for me the key moment
is actually what happens after ajax's death
what sophocles has the other greeks do
is debate about how they should proceed
and some argue that ajax should not be buried because of his actions
but odysseus steps in to argue that he should be buried
do not fling his body out unburied treated so unfeelingly
and don't let force have such control of you that you allow
your hate to trample justice down
for scholars this is the critical point in the play
there's a real danger in ajax
that because you've got these two extraordinary episodes
that are bloody and shocking
you think the play is about those two episodes
but i think the play is about the process of debate
that leads to decisions
in the wake of actions that really you haven't been able to cope with
so this is a play that stages debate
and it stages it in all its forms
one way of thinking about ajax is as a hermetical bronze age
or archaic warrior stuck in a much more modern political system
he has values about being an individual and being a hero
not being a cooperative person
that make him very difficult
as if individuals can no longer be powerful figures in a democracy
a man out of time out of place yes
so this may be someone who is hardly a role model citizen
but there are going to be lots of people in athens
who are hardly role model citizens
athens no doubt had its own fair share of bigheads
and glory seekers people who just wouldn't work within the democracy
and this play plays out the dilemma
of what do you do with those kinds of people
how do you keep the democracy on track
and that for me is why odysseus' intervention is so crucial
because he shows that you need to have empathy with these people
and you need to let justice run its course
odysseus offers a way for the community
to come back together make a joint decision and move forward
and that's why this play is such a great example
of what theatre did in ancient athenian society
it told a story it posed problems
it asked questions questions of the audience
about what would you do in this kind of situation
a situation which they would undoubtedly have to face up to
at some point in their lives
theatre was vital to the processes that played out
here on the pnyx home of the athenian assembly
it was the oil that allowed democracy to function
a contained space which allowed for a continual process
of risky reflection selfdoubt and debate
it's no accident that the most important words
in any greek tragedy are ti draso
what shall i do
theatre and democracy had grown up together
and were now inextricably linked in athenian minds
and every year for almost the next two centuries
the athenians came to the theatre
to rework the old myths into tragic dramas
that spoke to the problems that had beset
and were fundamental
to one of the most important and interesting stories in history
the rise and fall of athens
and at the same time those very same people were here
in the assembly making the decisions
that affected those events
it's therefore no surprise
that a common subject matter in athenian drama
was a problem that constantly dogged the athenian assembly war
and one war in particular fired the imagination
of the playwright aeschylus
who lived through the real life drama
and was inspired to write what is now
the first ancient greek play to survive in full
in 490 bc less than 20 years after the democracy was established
athens was attacked by the greatest power on earth the persian empire
the first crisis came at marathon 26 miles from the city of athens
a persian fleet arrived with an enormous army
although outnumbered the athenians attacked
and against all the odds they triumphed
the athenian dead were commemorated by a memorial barrow
near the battlefield
which is impressive even today
but ten years later the persians were back with an army
said to have been more than a million strong
as it bore down on athens the assembly passed a heroic decree
at the urging of a leading general called themistocles
amazingly a later copy of the decree
actually survives in an athens museum
this is one of the most evocative inscriptions surviving to us today
it's a decree of the people of athens and here's the key word
salamina salamis
this is the decree recording the decision
by the athenian people to evacuate their home city
and go to the island of salamis
to save themselves from the invading hordes of persians
this is the record of one of the most key moments
in the whole of ancient history
the athenians abandoned their city and took to their ships
leaving only a few men barricaded on the acropolis
the persians ransacked the city destroying the temples
but the athenian gamble paid off
the athenian fleet defeated the persians
in the narrows off salamis
greece was saved
and witnessing it all not from afar but at close range was aeschylus
aeschylus wasn't just a playwright he was also a soldier
he stood in the athenian ranks on the plane at marathon
on that fateful day when the persians first arrived
he was part of the victorious athenian army
but he also lost his brother on the battlefield
aeschylus in his own epitaph
preferred to be remembered for his role here at marathon
rather than for his plays
without doubt it was his extraordinary experiences
here on the battlefield that gave him a unique perspective
and allowed him to represent war on stage
in a way that has echoed ever since
aeschylus composed over 90 plays in his lifetime
and of the few that survive
the play that he composed about these great events
is one of the most moving and one of the most fascinating
in 472 bc aeschylus produced a play called the persians
and it's the first ancient tragedy to survive to us in full today
its sponsor was noone less than the future democratic hero pericles
but what's really surprising about it is its subject matter
because it tells the story of how the persians
reacted to the news of their defeat at the battle of salamis
a battle that those in the audience had fought and won
just eight years before
the play is set in the persian capital
a messenger arrives at the persian court
with the news of the greek victory
the persians cannot believe that they have been defeated
and they fall to pieces
in their misery
they summon the ghost of the previous king darius for advice
the ghost of darius tells the persians
that they themselves are to blame for their defeat
because their pride and their ambition
has led them to disregard the gods
the voiceless heaps of slaughtered corpses shall eloquently show
that no one human should puff up inflated thoughts
you see how insolence once opened into flower
produces fields ripe with calamity
and reaps a harvesthome of sorrow
this is the crucial theme of the play
well i think really at its heart it's almost a tragedy about hubris
hmm this idea of sometimes translated as arrogance
something like that going too far crossing a line transgressing
and the persians had done that
they thought big they thought they could go and take greece
they didn't win and actually
part of what the play is exploring
is the idea that big empires can fall
what kind of resonance
and implications does a play like the persians have for us today
it deals with one of these eternal themes it looks at war
it looks at the destruction the loss
the risks you run if you go to war
they became really popular with the gulf war
and with the iraq war as well and this is a really interesting one
in some modern productions
what you get is costume that really tells you
that the audience should be making a link with contemporary war
what point is aeschylus making do you think with that
i mean this is an amazingly difficult question to answer
you can't even imagine how this must have felt for the audience
they'd had their city sacked they'd really come close
to being completely occupied by persia
this play is on one level really celebratory yeah
but you have to imagine it operating on another level as well
because there are incredibly moving speeches in this
the language isn't just victorious if you like
i think it tells us a lot about what tragedy is doing
it is complex and it doesn't make it easy on the audience
and it's really asking the society to reflect
this play for me is both an exception to normal tragedy
and a fantastic example of it
it's an exception because unlike most that focus on mythical stories
this focuses on real and recent history
but it's a fantastic example of what tragedy does
because it doesn't just allow the athenians
to gloat over their victory
instead it offers a warning
for the persians pride came before a fall
and at a time when athens and the athenians
were beginning to grow in their own power within the greek world
the play offers that same message
be careful or you too could end up just like the persians
this warning had a direct bearing on the current situation in athens
in the aftermath of the persian wars
athens reached the peak of her power and influence
and the fleet that had secured victory at salamis
now reached out across the aegean
athens became the leading citystate in a new antipersian alliance
but what began as a free coalition was soon under athenian control
the financial muscle at athens' command allowed it eventually
to turn the free alliance of greek cities and states
that had been brought together to wreak revenge on the persians
into an empire solely to support the glory of athens
and it was policed by the mighty
and yet brutal majesty of the supreme athenian fleet
the warchest for that free alliance
which had been kept on the sacred island of delos
was moved to athens placed on the acropolis
and eventually into a building the parthenon
which has today become synonymous with democracy and freedom
and yet which was originally built
with the bloodmoney of athenian empire
every year each city in the alliance or empire
contributed money in silver as tribute
and this money was displayed in the theatre in athens
at the great dionysia festival
but when any members of the empire refused these payments
athens sent a fleet to attack them
having an empire meant that the athenian assembly
was now making lifeordeath decisions
not just about themselves but about cities and peoples far away
who had no real say in the matter
these decisions were far from easy as the athenians discovered
when they had to decide how to deal with the city of mytilene
in 428 bc the city of mytilene
rebelled against the athenian empire
the athenian assembly met to decide how to respond
the hardliners wanted to execute every man
and enslave every woman in the city
the moderates just to execute the ringleaders
on the first day of debate
the athenian assembly sided with the hardliners
they even dispatched a trireme to mytilene to carry out those orders
and yet when they met on the second day
the athenian assembly started to doubt its own decision
and indeed they went on to reverse it sending a second trireme
which got there just in time
now these events not only brought great relief to the mytileneans
but it also brought home to the athenians the critical importance
of thinking through properly their decisions before taking action
dealing with life and death decisions like this
had always lain at the heart of athenian drama
and authors like the prizewinning sophocles forced the audience
to experience vicariously the consequences of sloppy thinking
in 442 bc sophocles won yet another victory at the city dionysia
with his play antigone
now sophocles was a man intensely involved
with the affairs of the athenian state
he had been a general and he would go on
to become one of its closest advisers
during its darkest hours in future years
and his play antigone deals with exactly this kind of thing
how to debate and argue through the difficult
and yet critical issues that face a city
and what can happen when it all goes terribly wrong
the play tells the sad story of oedipus' daughter princess antigone
when antigone buries the body of her rebel brother
she is following the law of the gods
but the city's law and her uncle king creon have forbidden it
creon is furious and condemns her to death
creon's son haemon who is in love with antigone
urges his father to reconsider
he argues that a city is not a city if it is the holding of one man
but creon is stubborn and uncompromising
he refuses to listen and refuses to back down
the play ends with antigone and haemon both committing suicide
and with creon facing the displeasure of his people
and of the gods
creon has to face the fact that his actions
and his alone have caused this disaster
all of greek tragedy stages dilemmas that cities under leaders have
where they're faced with either very bad luck
or very bad management or both
now at one end of that spectrum you've got oedipus
who has very very very bad luck he's doomed before he's even born
how do you react to that
how do you conduct yourself in a situation with very bad luck
right at the other end is the story of oedipus' daughter antigone
faced with the most incompetent leader in all of greek literature
and that is saying something
creon simply cannot put a foot right so sophocles is asking people
to think about what a good leader might be
through showing them the worst possible leader
and the athenians loved that
so much that antiquity said they made him general in response
creon is getting pretty a bad stick from edith
but there is a real sense in which the issue at the centre of the play
is an issue that arises even in athenian law
in athenian law if someone is a traitor
they are not to be buried
you have to take them beyond the borders
and you can then bury them outside
if you're a dimark in athens
and there is a dead body in your deign you are obliged to bury it
so immediately that clash of
yes you must bury it but no you can't
arises if the dead body happens to be a traitor
so this isn't a non issue this is a real issue
and creon may make a complete fist of resolving it
but he makes a fist because
there are two diametrically opposed justifiable views
and you then have to pick your way through these
due to his dogged determination for others to do
exactly what he wants his inability to listen to compromise
creon ends up paying the ultimate price
the loss of his family and his authority
it's a play about listening debate compromise
what it takes to be a leader
those are issues which of course had relevance
to the ancient athenians watching the play
but they're also issues that are relevant to any society at any time
that's what makes antigone so timeless
it's got universal appeal because it's about someone
fighting against the system and a system that's wrong
i mean that's how it gets picked up now
and that's what really appeals to modern audiences i think about it
a play like antigone
what kind of resonance does that have for us today
thinking about this adaptation that jean anouilh
produced in 1944 in france while it was being occupied by nazis
that's a real example where you've got this play
which is really taken on and championed by the resistance
how did it ever get permission to be performed
if it's such a play of resistance
well i think that's the ambiguity of the play
so for the occupying force for the vichy government
actually you can look at this play and think
this is a play about law and imposing law
and actually this is a silly little girl
who breaks that law and she gets what's coming to her
so it's that ambiguity that allows even in those circumstances
this great play of resistance for some people to be put on
tragedy was an effective way of engaging with the issues
that beset the democracy but it was not the only way
there was also comedy
comedy was irreverent rude and bawdy
and it was also personal targeting real individuals
and just like today ordinary athenians in the marketplace
were deeply suspicious of their elected political leaders
some people it seems were just naturally born
to successfully navigate
the slippery waters of athenian politics
and one of those guys was a man called cleon
he speaks greek
now cleon was what we would call today an opportunistic politician
he would be with the aristocrats or he would be spurring
on the lowest of the low of the athenian citizenry
and the ancient commentators are fairly hard on cleon
today we'd probably be a bit more balanced
but without a shadow of a doubt
he would do whatever it took to get whatever he wanted
naturally he had his enemies
they accused him of being greedy not just for power
but for freshcaught tuna
seen back then as a luxury desired by the rich and antidemocratic
how could the democracy keep people like this in check
while not killing off their energy and enthusiasm
that at the end of the day benefited the city
well one of the ways they did it was in the theatre
by taking the piss out of them right in their very face
comedies while performed at the dionysia festival
also had their own smaller festival
it was called the lenaia
it took place early in january
long before the season for sailing started
so there were no foreigners present
this meant that comic writers could really let rip
without letting the city down
what you have is really lively plays
very outrageous plays sometimes
but they are politically involved
the settings can be amazing in the real sense incredible
you have comedies that go to the underworld
they go to hell
and that's where you get these animal choruses like frogs
this is a frog that was used
in the king's college greek play
animal choruses are quite common in comedy
you've got for example the chorus here
these guys performing and the songs that they get to sing
i mean this is a great source of comedy
what kind of level of biting satire are we talking about here
in ancient comedy
it's extremely personal
there's insults really of quite an infantile nature
you have plays which put politicians as one of the characters
very thinly disguised
but they'll be the leading politicians of the day
their policies will be clear the way they speak might be parodied
even the mask can reflect characters from athenian society
this was the sort of thing that lay in store
for ambitious politicians like cleon
and the man who was the real expert at this
was a comic playwright called aristophanes
and for aristophanes and cleon it was a grudge match
they even came from the same village
in 425 bc aristophanes wrote a play called the knights
it portrays cleon as a cunning servant
working for an old man called demos
demos represents the people and as his crafty servant
cleon misuses his position
for the purposes of extortion and corruption
yet in the end is it demos who has the last laugh
cleon's corrupt ways are exposed he loses his position
and he is reduced to selling sausages
outside the athens' city gates
aristophanes didn't pull any punches
this play brings cleon right back down to earth
and of course the politicians
about whom the jokes were being made
were right here visible to all in the audience
so it's like having one of our shows
the daily show in the states or have i got news for you here
being played out in an important civic space
the capitol or the house of commons
with the people they're taking the piss out of
sitting right here in the audience
having to take it in front of everyone
the greeks even had a word for this
they called these people the komedoumenoi
those made fun of in comedy
and this isn't just some sort of sideshow
this many ancient commentators saw
as the hallmark of ancient athenian democracy
and of freedom and free speech
the laughter didn't stop cleon's career
despite his slippery reputation he was elected again and again
but the effect of comedy was more subtle than that
what it did do was police the boundaries of behaviour
skewer pretensions and remind those in positions of power
of their responsibilities and of the limits of their ambitions
it's a kind of satire that we can still see at work
in our own democracy today
by the time of cleon this experiment in athenian democracy
was heading towards its centenary
and in that time it had seen it all from fighting for survival
to cultural supremacy to empire to wealth
and it was still at war not now with persia
but with greece's greatest fighting force the spartans
and desperate times called for desperate measures
the war between sparta and athens started in 431 bc
and lasted for decades
it was a fight to the death
sparta ruled by land athens ruled at sea
but there was one island
that had never submitted to athenian domination
and tried instead to remain neutral
the small island of melos
in 416 bc the athenian democrats had had enough
it was time for the melians to submit
so the athenians sent their fleet to enforce their demands
now according to thucydides the contemporary athenian historian
the athenians sent in not just their fleet
but also some diplomats to put the case
the case was very simple it was this join us or die
but what happened next according to thucydides
was an extraordinary debate between the two sides
these envoys the melians did not bring before the popular assembly
but bade them tell in the presence of the magistrates
and the few what they had come for
the envoys gave the melians an ultimatum
surrender and pay tribute to athens or be destroyed
the melians argued that they were a neutral city not an enemy
and that it would be shameful and cowardly to submit without a fight
but the athenians were unmoved
they countered that if they didn't extract surrender from melos
the empire would look weak
they argued that the strong have the right to exert their authority
this is a classic example
of what we call in greek an agon a debate
you could have seen it in the philosophical lecture hall
or in the political assembly or in the law courts
or indeed on the stage in the theatre
and it's summed up well it's summed up rather well actually
by an enthusiastic student who seems to have had this copy before me
and who has written rather pithily in the margin might is right
and that was the athenian argument
the strong do as they can
the weak suffer what they must
and that's exactly what happened
the athenians invaded the island of melos
they executed all the men
they enslaved all the women and the children
and they established an athenian colony there
and yet just the very next year in the theatre of dionysus
in the centre of athens
euripides the enfant terrible of athenian drama
staged a play called trojan women
its subject matter was what happened to the women at troy
after the greeks had besieged invaded and destroyed the city
so the athenians sat down to watch a play
which laid before them on the stage
the tragic reality of what they had done
just the year before to the island of melos
the play is set in the aftermath of the legendary siege of troy
the city has fallen all the trojan men are dead
and the surviving trojan women
who make up the chorus in the play are to be sold into slavery
but for princess andromache there's worse
her son is to be taken from her and slaughtered
when she argues the messenger tells her to be brave might is right
she wails
women all scream
man hush
she pants
if you say words that make the army angry
the child will have no burial
and without pity
so bear your fate as best you can
then you need not leave him dead without a grave
and you will find the greeks
more kind
trojan women may well have spoken to athenian actions on melos
but euripides was also crucially
sending a broader message about the disillusionment
that was taking hold in greece
after years of relentless savage war
and the terrible impact
that such conflict has on all members of society
why should we think that what the athenians did to the melians
would have generated such terrific outrage
when the spartans had done something
very similar to the people of hisiai just a few years earlier exactly
i mean that's purely historically
on the other hand the coincidence of date means
it seems to me that as euripides is writing this
what is the big campaign the athenians are involved in
that is going to involve women as slaves of war
well there is no other campaign going on
as euripides is writing it in the winter of 4165
but he could have thought it at any time that's the thing
by 416/415 i think euripides really has seen that war
as a way of life brings nothing but misery
to both victors and vanquished
and from that point of view if you focus on melos
you actually miss that point exactly
the more you think that this is a sort of
oh there's been a terrible atrocity yes exactly
the more you miss
that this is about war and how irrational and terrible
euripides is presenting a view of all the greeks
as having barbarised themselves
during the course of the peloponnesian war
euripides was not the only one
to despair at the state of affairs in greece
or criticise athenian behaviour
many in greece now felt that athens was guilty of hubris
of overreaching pride
and anyone who had ever seen a greek tragedy
would have been aware of what could happen next
here at rhamnous in the 6th century
the people had built a temple
to the greek goddess responsible for punishing those guilty of hubris
she was called nemesis a name that comes from the greek verb nemein
meaning to give what is due
now after the melian atrocity
it seemed like athenian ambition and pride
was beginning to overreach itself
they not only had enemies abroad
they had an increasing number of enemies in greece
and indeed an increasing number of enemies at home as well
who were beginning to think of democracy
as perhaps the immoral inversion of the righteous order
the question was
as the glorious golden age of the 5th century drew to a close
how would theatre and democracy
which had so spectacularly grown up together
survive in a much harsher and more difficult world
although the future of athens now looked uncertain
the past century had been a spectacular era
athens had invented and pioneered an array of things
which underpin our own civilisation
from classical sculpture and architecture
to new directions in philosophy and history
but for me out of all those legacies
two stand out as the most extraordinary
first democracy
athens created the first democratic constitution in history
which has become a beacon across the centuries
and second at the very same time
athens invented a powerful and incisive new art form
theatre an innovation without which perhaps
that democracy might never have survived
drama comes from the greek word dram to do to act to perform
and if there is one thing that has become abundantly clear
it's that theatre was never just mere entertainment
never a passive spectator
it was a performer in athens' story in the ancient world
from tragedy making our most important beliefs uncomfortable
to comedy questioning and policing citizenship
and keeping people in check
theatre was an institution that plugged into religious civic
political and military aspects of ancient athenian society
it was an extraordinary and extraordinarily uncomfortable
risky and yet essential part of athenian life
join the open university as we explore
the connections between greek theatre and modernday democracy
follow the links to the open university's freelearning website
subtitles by red bee media ltd